地球脉动 Ⅲ
字幕翻译 : 村儿南    修改 : foreverkeai
在墨西哥尤卡坦半岛之下
Beneath the Yucatan Peninsula of Mexico...
有一片别样的世界
..lies another world.
迷宫般的洞穴
A labyrinth of caves...
由淡水雕刻而成
..carved by freshwater...
淡水对地球上的生命至关重要
..and essential for life on Earth.
淡水塑造了大地 塑造了其中的万千生命
Freshwater shapes the land and the creatures that live in it...
以最令人惊讶的方式
..in the most surprising ways.
第 四 集
滴  水  之  源
哥斯达黎加的雨林
The rainforest of Costa Rica.
不难想见 这里大部分时间都在下雨
As you might expect, it rains most days.
但只有在雨季时
But it's only during the wet season
才会有如此倾盆大雨
that the rains become torrential.
伴随着滂沱的大雨
And with them...
一种非凡无比的生物出现了
..comes a most remarkable creature.
滑翔树蛙
Gliding tree frogs.
成千上万只树蛙涌来
Thousands drop in...
聚集在这片新形成的池塘中
..to gather at this newly-formed pond.
它们无不有着迫切的需要
They all have an urgent need.
繁殖
To breed.
雌性树蛙需要找一片树叶
This female needs to find a leaf
从而在其上产卵
and lay her eggs.
这场繁殖的热潮只将持续一天
The breeding frenzy will only last one day...
因此它得抓紧时间了
..so she needs to get a move on.
盼望得到垂青的雄性树蛙有很多
There are lots of eager males.
九名候选者竞争一个席位
Nine for every female.
全都蓄势待发
And all are ready to spring into action.
因此对于雌性树蛙来说 寻求伴侣不成问题
So, for her, getting a partner is no problem.
但失败者决定孤注一掷
But the other males are desperate.
对于雌性树蛙来说 求爱过程相当混乱
For this female, mating is rather chaotic.
事情有些失控了
Things are getting out of hand.
有一种解决方法
There is one way to deal with this.
踹它们几脚
A few well-placed kicks...
往往卓有成效
..usually does the job.
问题解决了
Problem solved.
现在雌性树蛙终于可以与伴侣结合
She and her partner can now finally mate...
在一片相对平静的环境下
..in relative peace.
树蛙产卵的位置
The eggs are positioned perfectly...
恰好位于池塘正上方
..directly overhanging the pond.
这里是理想的蝌蚪育婴室
This is the ideal nursery for tadpoles.
如今 雌性树蛙的工作已经完成
For now, her work here is done.
它将在明年大雨时分如期归来
She'll be back next year when the heavy rains return.
淡水的出现
As quickly as freshwater appears...
有时稍纵即逝
..it can vanish.
斯里兰卡东南部
Southeast Sri Lanka.
正当旱季中期
It's the middle of the dry season.
方圆数里内 这是唯一一处水坑
This is the only remaining water hole for miles around.
沼泽鳄
Mugger crocodiles -
长达五米的巨型鳄鱼
giants, five metres long.
十数只沼泽鳄
Dozens are hiding...
潜藏于水面之下
..beneath the surface.
还有更多鳄鱼
And others...
将来到此处
..are on their way.
这只雄性鳄鱼已经奔波了数小时
This male has been travelling for hours.
这片水坑是它唯一有机会
The water hole is the only place where he has a chance
捕食鹿的地方
to catch a deer.
只需捕食一只成年鹿 便足够沼泽鳄度过整个旱季
A single adult would be enough to feed him for the entire dry season.
但猎物也已知晓敌人环伺在周围
But hunting prey that knows you're here...
想要捕捉成功 就需要一些奇招
..requires something truly remarkable.
沼泽鳄布置了
He creates...
一个陷阱
..a trap.
它往泥里深挖
He digs down into the mud...
直到身形被植被隐藏
..deep enough to hide beneath the vegetation.
完美的伪装
Perfect camouflage.
沼泽鳄将陷阱布置在水边
He has built his trap right on the water's edge...
这里正是前来饮水的鹿的必经之处
..so it's the first place that thirsty deer will come to drink.
这些鳄鱼已经学会了如何利用
These crocodiles have learned to exploit
鹿对于淡水的迫切需求
the deer's desperate need for freshwater.
淡水不仅改变了动物的生命轨迹
Freshwater transforms not only the lives of animals...
还改变了整片地貌
..but entire landscapes.
每年 超过一万亿升水
Every year, over a trillion litres of water
流入卡拉哈里沙漠
flow into the Kalahari Desert.
水流自降雨地流到此处已经穿越了近两千公里
It has travelled a thousand miles from where it fell as rain.
水流的到来
And on arrival...
将卡拉哈里沙漠
..it turns the Kalahari...
变成了一片绿洲
..into a vast oasis.
奥卡万戈三角洲
The Okavango Delta.
淡水吸引着数以百万计的动物
These waters attract millions of animals.
对于一些动物来说 现在是组建家庭的绝佳时机
And for some, now is the perfect time to raise a family.
长脚水雉
A lily-trotter.
它也是一名尽责的父亲
And he is a father on duty.
雄性水雉养育着不止一只
He has not just one...
而是多达四只刚孵化的孩子
..but four newly-hatched chicks.
雏鸟六周后才能飞行
They won't be able to fly for another six weeks...
因此在那之前 只有成年雄性水雉才能保护它们
..so, until then, he alone is their protector.
水上行走并非易事
Walking on water is not straightforward...
因此雄性水雉要教雏鸟如何在睡莲上行走
..so he must show them how to be a lily-trotter.
高涨的水位使这里成为了绝佳的训练场
The floodwaters make the perfect training ground.
两周后
And in two weeks...
雏鸟不仅个头长大了一倍
..his chicks not only double in size...
信心也增加了一倍
..they grow in confidence.
但这里其实危机四伏
But this is a dangerous place to stray.
雄性水雉发出警报
He sounds the alarm,
雏鸟便立刻停了下来
and his chicks instantly freeze.
可它们还无法飞离险地
They can't yet fly to safety.
但雄性水雉还有一种手段来保护雏鸟
But there is one thing he can do to protect them.
一种风险极高的手段
And it's risky.
靠近鳄鱼以分散它的注意力
Get close enough to distract...
试图将其引开
..and hopefully divert the crocodile.
大功告成
Mission accomplished.
雄性水雉示意警报解除
He signals the all clear.
然而却少了一只雏鸟
But one chick is missing.
雄性水雉的呼唤
His calls...
没有得到回应
..go unanswered.
有些蓬头垢面 但好在没丢掉性命
A little bedraggled but alive and well.
这只雏鸟只是没有听到父亲的呼唤而已
His chick just hadn't heard his call.
危险来临时
And when danger threatens,
小心驶得万年船
its always better to be safe than sorry.
四只雏鸟在父亲的呵护下
He's brought his chicks, all four of them,
逐步迈向了独立的新生活
to the verge of independence.
虽然长脚水雉很好地适应了
Whilst lily-trotters are well adapted
这片被洪水淹没的世界
to life in this flooded world...
三角洲的另一批居民却还没有适应
..these residents of the delta are not.
非洲野犬
African painted dogs.
通常情况下 它们是极成功的猎手
Normally, they are remarkably successful hunters.
但这五只野犬已经好几天没吃过东西了
But this pack of five hasn't eaten in days.
寻找猎物并不是问题
Finding prey isn't the problem.
驴羚群就在数百米远处
This herd of lechwe is only a few hundred metres away.
但深不见底的水流挡住了去路
But between them is deep water.
从这里跨过去太危险了
It's not safe to cross here.
在陆地上 非洲野犬能以每小时60公里以上的速度奔驰
On dry land, the dogs can run at over 40mph.
但当驴羚遇到危险时 总是借助水域保护自己
But when threatened, lechwe always seek the safety of water.
它们有着分叉的蹄子和长长的后腿
With their splayed hooves and long hind legs,
能够在水中大步向前
they can power their way through the water.
非洲野犬却不行
The dogs can't.
非洲野犬虽然水性略逊
The pack won't be able to outswim the lechwe.
但它们有一种策略
But they do have a strategy.
非洲野犬将驴羚赶向自己的主场
The dogs drive the lechwe to where they have the advantage.
赶回陆地
Back towards dry land.
现在 野犬夺回了优势
Now the pack can regain lost ground.
今天是成功了 但明天能否继续成功还是未知数
Success today, but tomorrow the pack will need to hunt again.
在奥卡万戈三角洲
In the Okavango,
动物必须适应这里时有时无的淡水
animals must always adapt to the coming and going of freshwater.
但在一些罕见之处 比如马拉维湖
But there are a few rare places, as here in Lake Malawi,
淡水数百万年不间断的存在
where freshwater has lain for millions of years.
这使生命得以进化
And that has enabled life to evolve
形成了此处千姿百态的丰富物种
into a dazzling diversity of species.
这里孕育着数以千计不同的鱼类
There are over a thousand different kinds of fish here...
比地球上任何一处湖泊都多
..more than any other lake on Earth.
水中各色物种的竞争激烈异常
Competition in these waters is intense.
这是利氏雨丽鱼 也称迷彩鲷
Meet Nimbochromis livingstonii.
一名骗术高手
A master of deception
假装自己已经死了
that tricks other fish into thinking it's dead.
迷彩鲷身上斑驳的色彩看上去如同腐烂的肉体
Its mottled colouration mimics decaying flesh.
但想要装死
But to appear dead...
迷彩鲷必须
..one must at least...
如尸体般一动不动
..act dead.
这条年轻的迷彩鲷骗不到任何鱼
This juvenile is fooling no-one.
也许假装猝死会更可信
Perhaps faking his death will be more believable.
搞砸了
Blown it.
演技还需进一步打磨
A more subtle performance will be needed.
这次更逼真了
This is more convincing.
但显然还需要继续提高
But his aim must be better than that.
就差一点
Nearly.
看来得换一个地方了
It seems he's overstayed his welcome.
最后一次尝试
In a final effort...
迷彩鲷似乎甚至屏住了呼吸
..he appears to even hold his breath.
终于成功了
Success at last.
这一切需要生物百万年来的演化
All it took was a million years of evolution...
以及这片湖泊历久弥坚的稳定性
..and the unique stability of this ancient lake.
赤道非洲的西海岸外
Off the western coast of Equatorial Africa
坐落着比奥科火山岛
lies the volcanic island of Bioko.
这里的淡水十分汹涌
Freshwater here has a turbulent nature.
很少有生命敢于冒险入水
Few venture into such waters,
但风险越高 收益越高
but for those that do, there can be great rewards.
经过几个月的海中觅食与生长
After months feeding and growing out at sea,
这些虾虎鱼已经做好了繁殖的准备
these gobies are ready to breed.
最安全的产卵处
And the safest place to lay their eggs
是海洋捕食者无法染指的地方
is somewhere that ocean predators can't reach.
这座瀑布顶端
The top of this waterfall.
对鱼来说 无疑是一处不可能的目的地
Surely an impossible journey for a fish.
但在接下来的几天里 虾虎鱼会改变自己
But over the coming days, the gobies transform themselves.
颜色发生变化
They change colour.
嘴部转动 如同一个吸盘
Their mouth rotates and acts like a kind of suction cup...
这正是它们需要的
..which they will certainly need.
华山一条路 它们必须登上顶端
Because the only way...is up.
垂直落差高达30米
It is 30 metres to the top.
而虾虎鱼身长只有不到3厘米
They are only an inch long.
相当于人类去攀登
This is the equivalent of a human being scaling a waterfall
近两公里高的瀑布
over a mile high.
数以百万计的虾虎鱼向顶端进发
Millions attempt the climb...
但只有不到1%能成功登顶
..but less than 1% will make it.
这只虾虎鱼已经爬了好几天了
This goby has been climbing for days.
成功了
Made it!
抵达瀑布顶端的虾虎鱼现在可以准备繁殖了
Those that reach the top can now prepare to breed.
时机成熟时 虾虎鱼幼崽将被湍流冲回大海
And when the time comes, their young will be washed back out to sea.
流水的非凡力量
The extraordinary power of flowing water
使其成为地球上最伟大的建筑师
makes it our planet's greatest architect.
这里的地表看上去仿佛如同外星世界
This may look like the surface of an alien planet...
但这些奇异的图案实际上是通往海洋的
..but these strange patterns are channels of freshwater...
一条条淡水河道
..flowing towards the sea.
38亿年来
For 3.8 billion years,
自从第一滴雨水洒落大地
ever since the first rains fell...
淡水便无休止的循环往复
..freshwater has been making this journey.
然而今天 世界上三分之二的大江大河
But today, two thirds of our world's great rivers
已不再入海
no longer reach the sea.
地球上淡水资源有限
There is a finite amount of freshwater on Earth...
因此人类设计了非凡的方法
..so humans have devised extraordinary means
来确保有足够淡水满足我们的需求
to ensure that it is always available to meet our every demand.
我们如今大规模地
We now control freshwater...
控制淡水资源
..on a colossal scale.
地球上最大的灌溉系统
The largest irrigation system on Earth
建于巴基斯坦
has been built here in Pakistan.
这是一个由水坝和运河组成的巨大网络
A vast network of dams and canals...
从而从印度河中引水配水
..that diverts and drains the great Indus River.
整个系统被用来灌溉一片英国大小的区域
It's used to irrigate an area the size of England.
这片人造淡水世界
This man-made freshwater world
为数百万人
provides water and a livelihood
提供了水资源和生计
for millions of people...
但这是以自然世界的损害为代价的
..but at a cost to the natural world.
一种稀有的生物被困于灌溉渠中
A rare creature has become stranded in this irrigation canal.
渠中的水很快就将消失
And the water will soon be gone,
以供应周围土地的需要
used to supply the surrounding land.
这种生物濒临灭绝 数量不足2000只
Endangered, they number fewer than 2,000 individuals.
印度河豚
An Indus river dolphin.
这只雌性印度河豚的位置距离干流240公里
This female dolphin is 150 miles from the main river.
它无法靠自己的力量回去
She can't return on her own,
因此唯一的选择就是由救援队救走它
so the only option is for this rescue team to take her.
离开水 印度河豚无法生存太久
Out of water, she cannot survive for long.
回到河流的路途将花费数小时
The journey back to the river will take hours.
它的生命如今只能指望救援队
Her life now depends on these people.
仅一个月便有近30只印度河豚陷入危险 不得不依靠救援
Nearly 30 dolphins had to be rescued in one month alone.
淡水不仅是人类的资源
Freshwater is not only a resource for humans.
更是无数物种的家园
It is the home for countless species
没有淡水 便无法生存
that simply cannot survive without it.
淡水是地球的命脉
Freshwater is the lifeblood of Planet Earth.
幕
后
花
絮
为了拍摄最濒危的淡水河豚
To film the story of the most endangered freshwater dolphin,
「地球脉动」摄制组与世界顶尖专家乌兹玛·汗展开合作
the Planet Earth team joined the world's leading expert - Uzma Khan.
我第一次见到印度河豚时 简直惊呆了
The first time I saw Indus dolphin, I was just amazed.
它是一种美丽的生物
It's a beautiful creature, you know,
我对它一见钟情 它太独特了
it's like love at first sight. It's so unique.
20年来 乌兹玛一直在研究印度河豚的种群数量
Uzma has been studying the last remaining population for over 20 years.
那里有一只印度河豚冒出水面
There's a dolphin that surfaced just right there.
印度河豚只能存活于淡水中
Indus river dolphin can only live in freshwater.
只分布于巴基斯坦
It is only found in Pakistan and nowhere else.
印度河中只剩下约2000只了
And we only have about 2,000 of them left in the Indus River.
每一只印度河豚都弥足珍贵
So, you know, each individual is special.
在浑浊的水中跟随印度河豚十分困难
Following the dolphins in the murky water is extremely challenging.
它们跃出水面的瞬间稍纵即逝
They only surface for a split second
这也使得保护它们变得困难
and that makes protecting them difficult, too.
对它们最大的威胁是会被困在灌溉渠里
Their greatest threat is becoming trapped in the irrigation canals.
但乌兹玛也许有一种解决方案
But Uzma may have a solution,
她与救援队展开合作
and teams up with a rescue unit...
以尝试一些新东西
..to attempt something never done before.
这是我们第一次在亚洲的河豚上
This is the first time we'll be putting satellite tags
设置卫星标记
on river dolphins in Asia.
传感器还没有进行过这类物种的测试
Sensors has not been tested on this species,
虽然有点担心 但如果运行顺利
there's a little bit of anxiety, but if they work,
那么这将是物种保护工作的一个突破
then it's going to be a breakthrough for conservation.
十数年来 乌兹玛一直在开发一种合适的标记
Uzma has been developing a suitable tag for over ten years
希望这能帮助她收集
and hopes it will help her collect critical data
河豚如何跨越水坝和运河的关键数据
on how the dolphins are moving through the dams and canals.
但为了能够标记河豚 必须先有河豚得到救援
But in order to tag, she will first need a successful rescue.
这是我们今天的救援计划
This is the plan for ou rescue today.
每次救援时 我都很担心
I'm usually very concerned when a rescue is happening.
别让水进到呼吸孔里
Don't let water get in the blowhole
也别挤压河豚
and don't squeeze too tight.
潜水员实际上经验丰富
You know, the divers, they are very experienced,
但我总是会有些担心
but a part of me is always very worried.
它们是人类从未应对过的野生动物
They are wild animals that have never been handled.
救援队这项工作真的很冒险
It's really quite a risky thing that they're undertaking here.
河豚很有可能活不下来
There's a good chance the dolphin might die.
但如果不尝试救援
But, of course, they're balancing that against the fact
它们一定会死
that they definitely will die if they stay in here,
所以必须冒这个险
so it's a risk they have to take.
-他们救起河豚了吗 -是的 救起来了
Have they got the dolphin? Yeah, I think so. They've got it.
现在是生死时速
Now speed is key.
我们现在正全速赶往放生地点
We're now bombing across the field on the way to the release site,
我认为乌兹玛在我们前头
and I think Uzma went ahead of us, so I'm really hopeful
希望她能有机会设下标记
that she'll get her opportunity to tag the dolphin.
但救援任务有时也会偏离轨迹
But rescue missions don't always go to plan.
怎么回事
What happened?
轮胎被扎破了
A puncture.
过来 抬起床垫
Hey, come here! Grab the mattress!
河豚被快速转移到摄制组的车上
The dolphin is quickly moved to the film crew's truck.
把水箱拿过来
Bring the water tank!
把它放在更里面点
Put it further forward.
但由于没有遮蔽物
But with no roof for shelter,
河豚脱水而死的风险更高了
the dolphin is at greater risk of dehydration.
哪怕是现在 风险也很高
The stakes are high, even right now.
这是一只可爱的小动物 我们不希望它失去生命
It's a cute little animal and we don't want it to die.
慢点慢点
Slow, slow, slow.
团队改道前往距离最近的放生地点
The team re-route to the closest release site.
不能再拖了
There can be no more delay.
乌兹玛取消了标记计划
Uzma calls off the tagging.
这很不幸 因为我们已经做好了准备
It's unfortunate because we were all prepared,
一大早我们就准备就绪 非常兴奋
we were very excited since morning, all geared up,
希望下次救援行动能有机会设置标记
but hopefully we'll get an opportunity to tag the next rescue.
几天后 乌兹玛终于等到了机会
A few days later, Uzma finally gets her chance.
很激动的一天
It's a very exciting day for us.
好了
It's OK.
这一刻我们等待了十多年
The moment that we have been waiting for, over ten years.
冷静下来
Just stay calm.
好了 可以了
OK, it's good to go.
恭喜
Congratulations.
干得好
Well done.
我很高兴 特别高兴
I am very happy, very happy.
我认为这是个了不起的成就
I think it's a great accomplishment.
这是我人生中最高兴的一刻
It's the happiest moment of my life.
几周中 标记开始帮助我们能更多的了解印度河豚
Within a few weeks, the tags begin to reveal some new insights.
它们移动的很频繁 这是我们从未预料到的
They are moving quite a lot, which we never expected.
一只河豚从放生处逆流而上46公里之远
So one of the dolphins actually went about 46km upstream
还有一个新发现就是
from the release site, and the other thing is that we thought
我们本以为河豚会留在河流干流
that they will stay in the main river stream,
但实际上它们经常会游进支流中 特别有意思
but they are using side channels. It is extremely interesting.
追踪受标记河豚的动向
Tracking the movement of the tagged dolphins
将帮助乌兹玛更好的了解
will help Uzma better understand
它们被困的时间与地点
when and where they become trapped...
这将帮助保护这种濒危动物未来的生存
..helping safeguard the future of this most endangered animal.
下一集
Next time...
茂密的森林
..forests.
一片隐蔽的世界
A hidden world...
在这里 生命以出人意料的方式
..where lives are intimately entwined...
紧密地交织在一起
..in the most unexpected ways.
「栖息地探索者」生动地展现动物和它们的栖息地
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
探索这个免费互动程序并制作折纸动物
Explore this free interactive and make origami animals.
前往bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
点击链接进入开放大学
and follow the links to the Open University.
或者订购免费印刷版
Or to order a free printed version,
欢迎访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码
visit the website or call the number on the screen.